Register of the American subject collection, 1899-2004
Hoover Institution Archives
American Subject collection
1899-2004
XX742
Hoover Institution Archives
20 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize box, 1 oversize folder, 9 phonorecords, 7 phonotape cassettes (9.4 linear feet)
Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, memoranda, reports, letters, writings, and miscellany, relating to political and social conditions in the United States, and especially to socialist, libertarian and radical movements.
Access
Collection is open for research except for one folder in Box 3 that may only be used by persons that sign restriction agreement.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, clippings, other printed matter, memoranda, reports, letters, writings, and miscellany, relating to political, social and economic conditions in the United States, and especially to socialist, libertarian and radical movements.
Free enterprise.; Libertarianism--United States.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; Radicalism--United States.; Socialism--United States.; United States--History--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Video tapes.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1901-1994 (Box 1-12)
  Scope and Contents note
  Addresses, appointment books, articles, brochures, bulletins, campaign material, circulars, correspondence, directories, essays, invitations, financial records, flyers, leaflets, legislation, log-books, manuals, memoirs, memoranda, minutes of meetings, newsletters, newspaper issues, notes, pamphlets, proclamations, programs, reports, statements, studies, transcripts of testimony, tributes, clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - General. Serial issues, pamphlets, leaflets, bulletins newsletters, reports, directories, manuals, appointment books, memoranda, and copies of New Deal legislation, relating to political, social, economic, and military conditions in the United States, 1901-1989 (Box 1, 12)
  - American Friends Service Committee. Pamphlet relating to German refugees, and a button, n.d., that belonged to one Elizabeth Everett, 1939 (Box 8)
  - American Youth Congress. Clippings, relating mainly to activities of the American Youth Congress in the 1930s, 1935-1970
  - Anti-Semitism. Leaflets issued by the Edmondson (Economic Service), 1934 (Box 9)
  - Armed Forces
    - Instructional guide, entitled "AirLand Battle," relating to the theory of coordination of air and ground military operations
    - Pamphlets, one relating to defense production, and one relating to the threat of disease and non-battle injury to U.S. military personnel in the Gulf War of 1991, 1991 February 15, 1952
    - Miscellany. Two mimeographed technical training bulletins, European Theater,; one serial issue, 1949, issued by the Bureau of Naval Personnel; and one study, n.d., relating to motor vehicle operation in desert country and cold climates, 1945 June-July (Box 8)
  - Bicentennial. Addresses, illustrations, proclamations, and other material, l976, issued in commemoration of the Bicentenary of the United States (Box 2)
  - Business. Reprint of a speech by Susanna W. Purnell, relating to U.S. business abroad and the threat of terrorism, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Christians for Socialism. Tract, entitled "Commies for Christ," relating to similarities between Christianity and communism, and to guidelines for U.S. foreign policy, ca. 1983 (Box 8)
  - Civil rights movement. Pamphlets and leaflets, relating in particular to Martin Luther King, Jr., 1946-1967 (Box 12)
  - Communism. See also socialism (Box 8)
    - General. Correspondence, speeches, statements, testimonies, reports, studies, newsletters, pamphlets, brochures, and clippings, relating to international communism and to communism in the United States, 1946-1977
    - Issue of Left Review, organ of the John Reed Club of Philadelphia, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Cooperative movement. Pamphlets, 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Environment (Box 9)
    - General. Includes a brochure, describing the Earth Island Institute
    - Green parties. Flyer issued by the Green Party of California, 1991
  - Hoover, Herbert C. (Box 8)
    - Issue of The Illustrated Review, featuring Herbert Hoover, 1920 February
    - Printed articles, relating to Herbert Hoover's mining career in Australia at the turn of the century, 1987-1992
    - Tributes, presented to Herbert Hoover by the Bohemian Club, 1953-1954
  - LaRouche, Lyndon. Pamphlets, issued by Lyndon LaRouche groups, relating to world population policy and the electoral candidacies of LaRouche supporters, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Libertarianism (Box 2-3,)
  - General. Correspondence, reports, essays, financial records, notes, leaflets, pamphlets, bulletins, newsletters, newspaper and serial issues, and other printed matter, relating to libertarianism in the United States, the organization and activities of the Libertarian Party in California and other libertarian organizations and conservative youth groups, and the First National Convention of the Libertarian Party
    - First issue of the newsletter North Texas Libertarian, relating to the beginning of the 1986 Libertarian Party campaign in Texas, 1986 March (Box 8)
  - Merchant marine. Log-book (handwritten), for a voyage of the steam-ship Lottie Bennet from San Francisco to Valparaiso, Chile, 1914; and log-book (blank), for a voyage of the schooner W.F. Jewett from San Francisco to Callao, Peru, 1913 (Box 2)
  - Migrant labor - California. reprint of John Steinbeck's essay "Their Blood Is Strong," originally published in 1936 and relating to the migratory agricultural workers in California, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Minorities. Reprint of an article by Wendell L. Willkie entitled "The Case for the Minorities,", 1942
  - National Popular Government League. Bulletins, relating to various aspects of the political process, 1929-1940
  - Presidential inaugurations. Reception and concert invitations, programs, and campaign badges, relating to the inaugurations of Presidents Dwight D. Eisenhower and Richard M. Nixon, 1953-1973 (Box 4)
  - Prisons. Essay, by U.S. Bureau of Prisons director James V. Bennett, entitled "Of Prisons and Justice," relating to the penal system in general and to vocational training in prisons in particular, ca. 1960 (Box 9)
  - Protestant Episcopal Church. Clippings and other printed matter, relating to alleged Marxist influence in the Protestant Episcopal Church and in the World Council of Churches. Includes an Episcopalian study guide entitled "Struggling with the System: Probing Alternatives", 1974-1978 (Box 4)
  - Radicalism. Reports, relating to activities of the Workers' (Communist) Party, the Industrial Workers of the World, and other leftist organizations in Los Angeles during this period, 1924
  - Reform movements. Pamphlets, bulletins, and leaflets issued by various reform movements, 1943-1971 (Box 12)
  - Republican Party. Typescript memoir relating to the Republican National Convention of July 1952, and Earl Warren, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Richard M. Nixon. Written by a convention messenger. May be used only by persons agreeing not to disclose the identity of the author (Box 3)
  - Smith Act. Circular, relating to appeals for the defense of Oleta O'Connor Yates, under indictment on charges of violating the Smith Act, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Socialism (Box 5-7,12)
    - General. Pamphlets, leaflets, booklets, newspaper and serial issues, bulletins, clippings, reports, and minutes, relating to the Socialist and Communist parties, as well as to other radical movements in the U.S., and to Leon Trotsky and the onset of World War II, as viewed by the communist and Trotskyist press in the U.S. Includes a legal brief and a legal decision, as well as notes, l937-l94l, relating to legal proceedings against Harry Bridges, 1911-l967
    - Issue of The N.Y. Socialist, put out by the left wing of the Socialist Party and parodying The Socialist, the official organ of the party; and genuine issue of The Socialist, 1919 May 27, 1919 May 17 (Box 9)
    - Pamphlets, relating to Eugene V. Debs, 1920-1942? (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook of clippings, relating to Socialist candidates in the Presidential campaign of 1928 and Congressional and state elections of 1930, 1928-1930 (Box 9)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore. Program of memorial service, 1919 February 9 (Box 12)
  - Trade unions (Box 7)
    - General. Program of the Needle Trade Union, published by the Trade Union Education League, Needle Trade Section (in Yiddish), 1926
    - Handbills, 1931-1932, advocating unionization and unemployment relief in the U.S., and expressing pro-Soviet sympathies (some issued by the Communist Party of the United States of America)
  - Veterans
    - Bryant, M. C. Newspaper clippings, relating to the suicide of M. C. Bryant, an American businessman in France and a member of the American Relief Administration during World War I, 1928
    - Karling, F. Biographical sketch of F. Karling, Commander-in-Chief, Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States, 1918-1920
  - U.S. Holocaust Memorial Council. Brochure, relating to the work of the council and to the official groundbreaking of the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Wilson, Woodrow. Mimeographed copy of a letter, from President Woodrow Wilson to Jacob H. Schiff, head of the Jewish War Relief, relating to that organization's fund-raising campaign, 1917 November 22 (Box 8)
  - Miscellany. Two identical leaflets in Cambodian (possibly Thai or Laotian), dropped from an airplane over Stockton, California
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1936.
  Broadside issued by the Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League to Champion Human Rights
  - Broadside issued by the Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League to Champion Human Rights and entitled "High Holiday Boycott Proclamation," calling for a boycott of German goods and services as a way of fighting Nazi Germany and of helping to save the Jewish people from destruction. In English and Hebrew (Map-case Map case)
- AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIAL, n.d. and ca. 1929-1947
  Phonorecords and phonotape cassettes of speeches and statements by American presidents and others relating to American politics
  - Phonorecords (Oversize Record cabinet)
    - Inaugural addresses and other speeches by various presidents
      - Coolidge, Calvin (Item 1)
      - Hoover, Herbert (on agriculture and Prohibition) (Item 2-3)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Item 4)
      - Truman, Harry S (Item 5)
      - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Item 6)
      - Kennedy, John F. (Item 7)
      - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Item 8)
    - "Army Week Prayer" (delivered by Major General Luther D. Miller, Chief of Chaplains), produced by the Radio Section of the War Department Public Relations Division, with the cooperation of the Military Order of the World Wars, for Army Week, Includes a statement by General Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1947 April. (Item 9)
  - Phonotape cassettes. 7 phonotape cassettes of speeches on American politics and political parties by Frank Chodorov, John Hospers, Murray Rothbard, and Ludwig Von Mises (Oversize Cassette cabinet)
- Incremental Materials (Box 13-22)
  - Americans for Democratic Action file (Box 21)
  - Anti-Defamation League materials (Box 21)
  - Rest of collection not yet described